hey what's up guys my name is the Cho
and welcome back to my C++ series I know
this is weird I'm in like some Czech
Hotel just don't ask questions so today
we're going to be talking about what
static means inside a class or a struct
last time we talked about the static
keyword in C++ and what its meaning was
if it was outside of a class or a struct
and there's a link to that video in the
description below as well as a card on
the screen so go ahead and watch that
but today what does static mean if it is
inside a class or a struct in pretty
much all object Ed languages static
inside a class means a certain thing if
you use it with a variable it means that
there is only going to be one instance
of that variable across all instances of
the class so if I make a class called
entity and I keep making entity
instances I'm still only going to have
one version of that variable meaning if
one of the instances changes one of the
variable meaning if one of those
instances changes my static variable
it's going to reflect that change across
all instances because really there's
only one variable even though I've made
a whole bunch of class instances and so
because of that there's no point of
referring to the variable through a
class instance because there's like
there's like a global instance for that
class with static methods you get a
similar effect where you just you don't
have access to the class instance a
static method can be called without a
class instance and inside a static
method you cannot write code which
refers to a class instance since you
don't have that class instance to refer
to Let's jump in and take a look at some
examples examples so over here I'm going
to write a struct called entity and I'm
going to give it two integers X and Y
know that I'm using a struct here but
you could use a class it doesn't matter
the reason I've chosen a struct here is
because I want those X and Y variables
to be public and by using a struct
they're going to be public by default
I've made a video about the differences
between classes and structs as well if
you haven't seen that there's a link
everywhere check it out so right now we
have a pretty straightforward entity
class we can instantiate it like so set
the values to what we want them to B
such as 2 and three and we're ready to
roll if I want to make another instance
of that class I can also do that this
time I'll initialize it using an
initializer so we'll set it to like 5
and 8 for example and also let's give
our entity struct some kind of function
so that we can print what we have to the
console just using standard C
out and there we go so if I come down
here and I print e and
E1 the behavior here is going to be
fairly normal and what you would expect
so we should get 2 three and then 58 for
our second one and you can see that's
what we get however things will change
if I make the variable static so if I
come over here and I make these X and Y
static first of all my initializer here
will fail because X and Y are no longer
class members so we can forget about
that and rewrite our code to be this
which again is not strictly written
correctly however for an example it will
work make sure we're referring to E1
here so you can see we are referring to
two different instances or it appears to
be so at least if we run this code we're
going to get unresolved external symbols
because we actually have to define those
static variables somewhere and we can do
so over here by just writing int entity
which is the scope of these static
variables then the name of the variable
and we don't really need to set them
equal to anything if we don't want to we
can just write this so now that they've
been defined the Linker can link to the
appropriate variable and we can run our
code however if we do so you'll see that
we actually get 58 58 printing twice
which is a little bit weird you can see
here in our code that it clearly appears
that we're setting X and Y to 2 and 3
for the first instance but then 5 and 8
for the second one however remember that
those X and Y variables when we made
them static we made it so that there was
only one instance of those two variables
across all instances of our entity
classes which means that when I'm
changing the second entities X and Y
they're actually the exact same as the
first one they're pointing to the same
memory picture two different entity
instances however the X and Y that
they're pointing to are shared they're
pointing to the same X and Y and as such
there's no point in US referring to them
like this we can actually just refer to
them like this as if they were inside
the entity scope because really that's
all they are it's like we've made two
variables that are inside a namespace
called entity They Don't Really belong
to the class they do of course in the
sense that they can be private and
public and they have like so they are
still kind of part of a class and not
just a nam space but for all intents and
purposes they basically are just in a
namespace and they have nothing to do
with any kind of allocation when you
create a new class instance or anything
like that so if we were to rewrite our
code
correctly you can see this makes a lot
more sense now why we're getting 58
everywhere because we are actually
modifying the exact same variable this
is of course really useful when you want
to have variables across classes you
could of course just create a global
variable or instead of a global variable
it could be like a stack IC Global
variable right so it's still internally
linked and all that stuff it's not going
to be Global across your entire program
however doing that would have the same
effect of this so why would you do this
the answer is basically just it makes
sense to put it inside entity if you
have something if you have a piece of
information a piece of data that you
want to be shared across all entity
instances or it makes sense to actually
store it inside the entity class because
it's to do with entities for
organizational purpose says you're much
better making a static variable inside
this class rather than having some
static or Global floating around
somewhere static methods work in a
similar way if I make this print method
static then it's going to work fine
because you can see it's referring to X
and Y which are also static variables I
no longer have to call it like this I
can also call it like so in fact this
would be the correct way to call it and
of course you can also notice that it's
clearly going to be printing the same
thing because we're running the same
exact method twice and in this
particular example we don't even need
class instances at all because
everything we're doing is static however
things would break here if we decided to
make X and Y non-static but keep our
print method a static because static
methods cannot access non-static
variables and there's a very very simple
reason to that some people get a little
bit confused as to what static thing can
access what non-static thing it's really
not confusing at all check this out I'm
going to bring back my entity instances
and rewrite my code so that we actually
do have a separate X and Y for each
instance of the entity class I'm going
to still leave this print method as
static I'm going to get rid of this
definition of our static variables and
get rid of static in front of X and Y if
we were to try and compile this code now
we're going to get an error and you can
see our error reads illegal reference to
non-static member entity X because you
cannot access this from a static method
the reason is that a static method does
not have a class instance I might go a
little bit more into how classes
actually work in a future video but
essentially every method that you write
inside a class every non-static method
always gets an instance of the current
class as a parameter that's how classes
actually work behind the scenes there's
no such thing as a class they just
functions with a hidden parameter of
sorts a static method does not get that
hidden parameter a static method is the
same as if you wrote a method outside of
the class if I were to write a print
method out side here suddenly this
probably makes a lot more sense as to
why you can't access X and Y because you
don't know what they are now picture
that you had this exact same method
however an entity actually was passed in
as a parameter and your code was
converted to this suddenly this works
what we've just written here this method
that we've just written here is
essentially what a class method that is
non-static actually looks like when it's
compiled and so if we take away this
instance which is exactly what we're
doing when we add this static keyword to
a class method we get errors that's why
you're getting errors it doesn't know
which entities X and Y you want to
access because you haven't given it a
reference to an entity so hopefully that
makes a lot of sense and that clears
everything up next time we're going to
take a look at integrating this new
found static knowledge into our log
class that we've been working on if you
guys want to see what that looks like
you can look at the how to write a C++
class video as we go along with this
series we're going to keep adding to
that low class and figure out some new
things we can do and kind of keep keep
improving it as we learn new Concepts
static is incredibly useful for static
data data that doesn't change between
Class instances but that we actually
want to use in our classes thank you
guys for watching as always you can
follow me on Twitter and Instagram links
in the description below and if you
really like this series you can support
it on patreon.com Theo thank you to
everyone who's supporting this and
making this possible love you guys I'll
see you next time goodbye
[Music]
he